School of Communication fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
School of Communication fonds
1970 - 1996
F-92
2.51 m of textual records 25 photograph negatives
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
School of Communication
The School of Communication has built its curriculum and research around understanding the organization, operation and meaning of the communication messages on which personal, national and global associations are built and sustained.
The School had its origins in 1965 as the Centre for Communications and the Arts, a unit in the Faculty of Education which offered credit courses, non-credit workshops, and public events. In 1970, the Faculty of Education was reorganized. The Arts program separated from the Faculty of Education to become part of the Division of General Studies. It retained the organizational title of Centre for Communications and the Arts although it no longer offered academic courses in communication studies. These courses remained in the Faculty of Education and became part of that faculty's Educational Foundations Centre. In 1972 Communication Studies became a department of the newly created Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies. In 1977-1978, its name changed to the Department of Communication.
The School concentrated on six areas in the undergraduate program: theory and systems, history of communication, communication processes, communication media, political economy, and communication policy. In 1980, the School played an active role in founding the Canadian Communication Association (CCA). In 1981 a proposal was submitted to the Universities Council of British Columbia to establish a Ph.D. program in Communication. Approval for this program was obtained in 1983, making it the only Communication Department in Canada (west of Ontario) to offer a full set of academic degree programs (Ph.D., M.A., and B.A.) in the communication field. In 1984 the School consolidated its teaching and research areas, focusing on three areas of specialized concentration: communication media, technology and policy.
In 1985 after the dissolution of the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, the School moved into the Faculty of Applied Sciences, in recognition of the fact that communication is a discipline of practical application. In 1994, the School adopted its current name, the School of Communication.
The School continues to be leader in local and international communication research and is involved in a number of projects including the Canadian Centre for Studies in Publishing (founded in 1987), Centre for Policy Research on Science and Technology (established in 1988), The Digest (an on-line journal published by the Centre for Policy Research on Science and Technology), Emergency Preparedness Information Exchange (operated by the Telematics Research lab), and NewsWatch Canada. The School also has a number of lab facilities that supporting research and communication development. These include the Assessment of Technology in Context Design Lab (ATIC-DL) created in 1997, the Emergency Preparedness Information eXchange Lab, the Media Analysis Lab and the Sonic Research Studio (home of the World Soundscape Project established at Simon Fraser University during the late 1960s and early 1970s).
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
The fonds consists of records relating to the activites of the School and its predecessors. Activites and events documented include the evolution of the department's structure, functions and governance; deliberation of School committees; correspondence of the Chair with staff, faculty, other university departments and external organizations; departmental research projects, proposals, and grant applications; curriculum development files and course files; and publications.
Records include correspondence and reports; meeting agendas, minutes and supporting papers; policies and procedures; course proposals and outlines, lecture notes and planning materials; conference photograph negatives; course guides, newsletters and annual reports (1993-1994).
The arrangement of the fonds into series and subseries was provided by the Archivist in June 2004. Series 5 (Curriculum files) is based on the creator's original groupings. Other series were established by the archivist to provide structure to the bulk of "general subject files" transferred by the creator.
Lewis, Brian; Anderson, Robert S.; Laba, Martin; Salter, Liora; Leiss, William; Melody, William H.; Smythe, Dallas; Brown, Robert C.; Mallinson, Thomas J.; Photographic materials; Textual records
The records were transferred to Archives in two accessions in 1999.
All accessions have been processed as of June 2004. Further accruals are expected.
Records relating to the School's predecessor, the Centre for Communications and the Arts, may also be found in the Faculty of Education fonds (F-22, subseries 22-8-1, 22-8-5) and The School for Contemporary Arts (F-109). Thomas J. Mallinson was Chair of the Centre for Communications and Arts from 1967 to 1969; his personal papers are held by the Archives as fonds (F-124). For records relating to the School's tenure in the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, see fonds (F-23, subseries 23-3-3) and for tenure in the Faculty of Applied Sciences, see fonds (F-154, not yet processed).
The fonds includes records containing personal information. Access to these files is restricted in accordance with the provisions of British Columbia's Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (RSBC 1996 c. 165). Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File list is available.
- School history files, 1979 - 1990; F-92-1; 11 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the evolution of the School, its internal organization, mandate and scope of activities, and departmental planning. Activities, events and topics documented include reorganization as part of the faculty of Applied Sciences in 1985, departmental review, an update on alumni and departmental open house, and planning for Homecoming '90. Records include correspondence; reports; proposals; planning documents; notes and working papers.
  This series was created by the archivist in June 2004 to provide structure to the creator's general subject files.
  Further accruals to the series are expected.
  For related historical records containing a Departmental Review from 1977, see "West Mall Complex space file" (sub-series F-92-3-1-0-10).
  Access to files containing personal information may be restricted in accordance with the provisions of British Columbia's Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (RSBC 1996 c. 165). Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review some files may be restricted in accordance with the FOI/POP Act. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - Internal review, 1979; F-92-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Faculty of Applied Sciences, 1984; F-92-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
  - Faculty of Applied Sciences university reorganization, 1984; F-92-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
  - Alumni network, 1986; F-92-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
  - Department open house, 1987; F-92-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
  - Review document: 1st iteration, 1987; F-92-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
  - Review document: "The Department of Communication, Simon Fraser University", 1988; F-92-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
    Restricted in part
  - Departmental review: 87-88 finalized, 1989; F-92-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
  - Homecoming '90, 1990; F-92-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
- Committee files, 1976 - 1990; F-92-2; 29 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to meetings and deliberations of departmental, faculty and university-wide committees in which the School participated. Series includes departmental meetings, committees responsible for departmental hiring, curriculum development, and undergraduate and graduate studies. Also included are records for the Faculty of Applied Science Executive committee, President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities, Downtown Campus Planning, and the Labour Program Advisory committee. Records include meeting agendas, minutes and supporting documents; correspondence; reports; policies and procedures; program and course proposals and revisions; and working papers.
  Note that in the case of departmental committees, the files constitute the original, authoritative records of those committees. In the case of non-departmental committees (faculty and university), however, the School did not typically function as the official record-keeper or custodian of the committee's original records; accordingly, these files document the School's participation in the committees (correspondence and copies of committee records) rather than representing the authoritative record of those committees.
  This series was created by the archivist in June 2004 to provide structure to the creator's general subject files. Each committee has been assigned a separate sub-series. Committees have been grouped into the following types: Departmental, Faculty, University. Within each sub-series, files are arranged chronologically.
  For other material related to curriculum development, see "Curriculum files" (sub-series F-92-5-1); for course content, see "Course files" (sub-series F-92-5-2).
  - Departmental meeting files, 1979 - 1990; F-92-2-1; 3 cm of textual records
    - Departmental meetings, 1979 - 1983; F-92-2-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-1)
    - Departmental meetings, 1984 - 1990; F-92-2-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-2)
  - Departmental Hiring Committee files, 1989; F-92-2-2; 2 cm of textual records
    - Hiring Committee, 1989; F-92-2-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-2)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee files, 1976 - 1985; F-92-2-3; 7 cm of textual records
    - Department of Communication Undergraduate Curriculum Committee binder, vol. 1, 1976 - 1979; F-92-2-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-2)
    - Department of Communication Undergraduate Curriculum Committee binder, vol. 2, 1976 - 1979; F-92-2-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-2)
    - Department of Communication Undergraduate Curriculum Committee binder, vol. 3, 1976 - 1979; F-92-2-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 92-2)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum Task Force, 1985; F-92-2-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 92-2)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Committee files, 1980 - 1985; F-92-2-4; 3 cm of textual records
    - Undergraduate Committee correspondence, 1980 - 1981; F-92-2-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-2)
    - Undergraduate Committee correspondence, 1982 - 1985; F-92-2-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-3)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee files, 1976 - 1984; F-92-2-5; 5 cm of textual records
    - Graduate Studies Committee, vol. 1, 1976 - 1982; F-92-2-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-3)
    - Graduate Studies Committee, vol. 2, 1976 - 1982; F-92-2-5-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-3)
    - Graduate Studies Committee: reports and submissions, 1983 - 1984; F-92-2-5-0-3 (Archival box - standard 92-3)
  - Faculty of Applied Science Executive Committee files, 1985 - 1986; F-92-2-6; 2 cm of textual records
    - Faculty of Applied Sciences: Executive Committee, 1985 - 1986; F-92-2-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-3)
  - University - President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities files, 1984; F-92-2-7; 5 cm of textual records
    President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities
    - Submission to President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities (PACUP), 1984; F-92-2-7-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-3)
    - Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies (FIDS) internal review - report to PACUP, 1984; F-92-2-7-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-3)
    - PACUP - final round, 1984; F-92-2-7-0-3 (Archival box - standard 92-3)
  - University - Downtown Campus Planning Committee files, 1987 - 1989; F-92-2-8; 2 cm of textual records
    Downtown Campus Planning Committee
    - Downtown Campus Planning Committee, 1987 - 1989; F-92-2-8-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-4)
  - University - Labour Program Advisory Committee files, 1983 - 1986; F-92-2-9; 2 cm of textual records
    Labour Program Advisory Committee
    - Labour Program Advisory Committee, 1983 - 1986; F-92-2-9-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-4)
- Chair's correspondence, 1970 - 1989; F-92-3; 34 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the Chair's/Director's correspondence with School program areas and faculty, other university departments and external (non-university) individuals and organizations. Activities, events and topics documented include policy development, faculty and student relations, reference letters, graduate student review, facilities and space planning in the West Mall Complex, collaboration with other university departments and research and consulting for external organizations. Records include correspondence; reports; notices; letters; invoices; newsletters; proposals; and working papers.
  This series was created by the archivist in June 2004 to provide structure to the creator's general subject files. Correspondence has been grouped into the following sub-series by type: Departmental, University, External.
  - General departmental correspondence, 1970 - 1989; F-92-3-1; 22 cm of textual records
    - Communication Studies binder, vol. 1, 1970 - 1978; F-92-3-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-4)
      Restricted in whole
    - Communication Studies binder, vol. 2, 1970 - 1978; F-92-3-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-4)
      Open
    - Chairmanship of department, 1971 - 1989; F-92-3-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 92-4)
    - Communications graduate student review, 1981 - 1984; F-92-3-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 92-4)
    - Leiss - chronological correspondence, 1984 - 1985; F-92-3-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 92-4)
    - Salter - chronological correspondence, vol. 1, 1985 - 1987; F-92-3-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 92-4)
    - Salter - chronological correspondence, vol. 2, 1985 - 1987; F-92-3-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 92-5)
    - Salter - chronological correspondence, vol. 3, 1985 - 1987; F-92-3-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 92-5)
    - Salter: log file, 1989; F-92-3-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 92-5)
    - West Mall Complex space file, 1977 - 1981; F-92-3-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 92-5)
    - West Mall Complex (space) file, 1981 - 1983; F-92-3-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 92-5)
    - Faculty of Applied Sciences: office automation, 1982 - 1984; F-92-3-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 92-5)
  - University correspondence, 1971 - 1985; F-92-3-2; 5 cm of textual records
    - President's office correspondence, 1976 - 1983; F-92-3-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Dean of Interdisciplinary Studies (IDS), 1979 - 1984; F-92-3-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Teaching Support Staff Union (TSSU), 1971 - 1983; F-92-3-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Faculty of Education [high school mentoring], 1976 - 1982; F-92-3-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Faculty of Applied Sciences (FAS): Engineering, 1979 - 1985; F-92-3-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
  - External correspondence, 1978 - 1988; F-92-3-3; 7 cm of textual records
    - Information re: CMNS Dept. (The Jim Pattison Group), 1988; F-92-3-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Salter: pesticides report, 1984 - 1985; F-92-3-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Salter: equality in the media, 1978; F-92-3-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
      Open, no restrictions
      Access review (Sep 12, 2022) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
    - Salter: Task Force on Broadcasting, 1985 - 1987; F-92-3-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Salter: Methods of Regulation (A Report to Task Force on Broadcasting), 1986; F-92-3-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Salter: "Submission to Royal Commission on Health and Protection in Uranium Mining", 1980; F-92-3-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
    - Salter: "Value of Service Pricing: An Examination of Options for Regulatory Policy", 1987; F-92-3-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 92-6)
- Departmental research projects, proposals and grant application files, 1976 - 1989; F-92-4; 35 cm of textual records 25 photograph negatives; Physical description: 25 photograph negatives located in F-92-4-0-4
  Series consists of records relating to research projects, proposals and grant applications prepared by faculty members during the course of university-wide, national and international research on communication. Project topics include Media Analysis, Image / Sound Research Centre, Laboratory for Computer and Communications Research, conferences, communication databases, the Telecommunications Research Group and the Radio Spectrum Project. Grant applications include those sent to the President's Research Fund, SSHRCC and NSERC. Records include application forms; proposals; correspondence; reports; faculty curriculum vitae; working papers; financial budgets; statistics; contracts and agreements.
  - Image / Sound Research Centre (Media Analysis Lab: Gruneau), 1987 - 1988; F-92-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
  - Project: Asia Pacific Conference [and other proposals], 1988; F-92-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
  - CCT Conference - correspondence and financial information, vol. 1, 1986 - 1987; F-92-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
    Open with enclosures
    Access review (Sep 12, 2023) – The bulk of the file is open. However, it includes a small number of documents (3) that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (employment history, educational history). Restricted documents have been removed (enclosed); the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - CCT Conference - photo negatives, vol. 2, 1986 - 1987; F-92-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - small 92-21)
    Textual records; Photographic materials
  - Canadian Communication Information Consortium (CCIC) (database), 1986 - 1987; F-92-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
  - Media Analysis Lab, 1985 - 1987; F-92-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
  - Communication / communication technology research at SFU, 1981 - 1983; F-92-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
  - Current projects, proposals, 1985; F-92-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
  - President's Research Fund applications, 1985 - 1986; F-92-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
  - Faculty of Applied Sciences (FAS): current projects, 1985 - 1986; F-92-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 92-7)
  - Research initiatives (participation in research centres), 1989; F-92-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - Project proposal: Latin American Exchange, 1984 - 1985; F-92-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - SFU / Australia project, 1986; F-92-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - Salter / Lorimer transcom project, 1987; F-92-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - Laboratory for Computer and Communications Research (LCCR), 1982 - 1983; F-92-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - Student data project, 1986; F-92-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - SFU / University of Montreal: databank of information related to broadcasting, 1986; F-92-4-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - Apple Canada Education Foundation, 1984 - 1985; F-92-4-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - Salter / Anderson: updated and improved version of the database CEDARS, 1986 - 1987; F-92-4-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - Radio spectrum project, 1984; F-92-4-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - International Research Development Centre (IDRC), 1986 - 1989; F-92-4-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - Telecommunications Research Group, 1976 - 1983; F-92-4-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
    Restricted
    Access review (Sep 12, 2022) – File includes records that contain the personal information of identifiable indviduals (employment history, educational history, financial history, medical/psychological history, third party opinions about individual). File restricted in whole, but may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - Telecommunications Research Group, 1983 - 1985; F-92-4-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
    Open with redactions
    Access review (Sep 12, 2022) – The bulk of the file is open. However, it includes a small number of documents (1) that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (educational history). Restricted documents have been removed (enclosed) and redacted; the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - "Improving Risk Communication in the Press": William Leiss and R. Smith, 1988; F-92-4-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - SSHRCC: Discourse on Risk, 1985 - 1989; F-92-4-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 92-8)
  - SSHRCC: The Discourse on Risk: Case Study of Alachlor Controversy (Leiss), 1988 - 1989; F-92-4-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 92-9)
  - SSHRCC: research grants (misc.), 1985 - 1986; F-92-4-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 92-9)
  - NSERC major installation equipment and infrastructure grant application, 1983; F-92-4-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 92-9)
- Curriculum files, 1975 - 1992; F-92-5; 1.37 m of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the credit and non-credit instruction offered by the School and its predecesors, including new course proposals, curriculum rationalization and scheduling, grading, reading lists, assignment and essay questions, lecture schedules and outlines, examinations, cross-listed courses with other departments, guest lecture series, graduate level colloquiums, directed studies proposals, continuing studies courses offered downtown, and the Ph.D. program proposal. Records include correspondence; reports; course files; working papers; and policies.
  Some teaching material has been retained (e.g. glossaries, lecture notes), but reprints of articles have not been preserved. The sub-series on "Course files" does not include course administrative records (e.g. enrollment lists, book requisition forms, grade change forms, registration status reports, waiting lists, add/drop form, lab fee notices). Note that record types found in the files vary considerably from course to course.
  Series is arranged into sub-series that make a distinction between those files that relate to general curriculum planning and specific course files. The material has been arranged according to the original filing system of the creator. Course files are arranged chronologically by course number and year.
  The School's published handbooks contain additional program and course descriptions; see "Course outline booklets" (series F-92-6-0-0-3).